Charles E. Waltensperger
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Charles E. Waltensperger papers
1893-1931
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Waltensperger, Charles E.
1.2 linear feet
This small collection of scattered papers of painter and illustrator Charles E. Waltensperger measures 1.2 linear feet and dates from 1893-1931. Papers include biographical material, scattered correspondence between family members, sales records, engagement diaries, notes, sketches of the human form, printed material, and photographs of Waltensperger, his family, colleagues, and travel scenes.
Provenance
The Charles E. Waltensperger papers were donated in 1973 by the artist’s brother, George Waltensperger, through Mrs. Beverly Bassett who was conducting a survey of Michigan artists. In 1979, two photographs and two letters were donated.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Use requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Charles E. Waltensperger was born on April 10, 1871 in Detroit, Michigan, the son of Emily and Fred Waltensperger, a merchant.
Waltensperger studied art at the Julius Melchers School with fellow students Joseph Kraemer, Myron Barlow, and Fred Leipziger. While working as an elevator operator for the Detroit Free Press, Waltensperger made sketches of the passengers. This attracted the attention of publisher William E. Quinby, who was so impressed with his drawings that he paid Waltensperger’s tuition at the school of the Detroit Museum of Art.
During the early 1890s, Waltensperger exhibited his work in a competition at the Detroit Institute of Arts and was awarded a James E. Scripps scholarship that financed his art studies for two years in Europe. He studied both at the Académie des Beaux Arts under Jean-Léon Gérôme, and at the Académie Julian in Paris in 1893. Upon his return to the United States, Waltensperger was employed as a commercial artist and worked as an illustrator for the Detroit Free Press. He also illustrated books written by M. Quad, the pseudonym of humorist Charles Bertrand Lewis.
Waltensperger later established his own studio and turned his interest to creating oil paintings, primarily of Dutch interiors. He traveled extensively in Europe and in New England. He was a member of a group of Detroit artists known as the Hopkin Club that held exhibitions at the Old Detroit Museum of Art before they established the Scarab Club.
Waltensperger never married and during the last five years of his life, ill health forced him to curtail his travels. He died of a heart attack on December 12, 1931 in Detroit.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of painter and illustrator Charles E. Waltensperger date from 1893-1931 and measure 1.2 linear feet. Biographical material includes passports and membership cards, including one for the Scarab Club. Letters are generally from members of the Waltensperger family discussing travels. One letter from Waltensperger briefly mentions his studies at the Académie des Beaux Arts and his instructor, Jean-Léon Gérôme, “who is perhaps the best that ever happened. He is very severe and no fancy stuff goes with him.” Business records consists primarily of receipts, but also include account books documenting sales. Also found within the papers are annotated engagement diaries, notebooks that contain addresses, notes about art, and annonated sketches, and miscellaneous notes. There is one folder of Waltensperger's artwork consisting of sketches of the human form. Printed material including clippings and exhibition catalogs relating to Waltensperger and others. Photographs found here are of Waltensperger, his family and friends, and scenes from his travels.
Index Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following index terms
Subjects:
Gérôme, Jean Léon, 1824-1904; Académie des beaux-arts (France)-- Students
Subjects-Topical:
Painters--Michigan--Detroit; Illustrators--Michigan--Detroit
Types of Materials:
Sketches; Photographs
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 8 series:
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1905-1931 (Box 1; 2 folders)
Series 2: Letters, 1899-1931 (Box 1; 19 folders)
Series 3: Business Records, 1925-1931 (Box 1; 4 folders)
Series 4: Engagement Diaries, 1914-1931 (Box 1; 6 folders)
Series 5: Notes and Writings, 1913-1931 (Box 1; 8 folders)
Series 6: Artwork, circa 1890-circa 1930 (Box 1; 1 folder)
Series 7: Printed Material, 1896-1931 (Box 1; 19 folders)
Series 8: Photographs, circa 1890-circa 1930 (Box 1, 2; 25 folders)
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Material, 1905-1931, Series 1:; (Box 1; 2 folders)
  Biographical material consists of three passports, identification cards, a voter’s registration card, and membership cards for the Detroit Young Men’s Christian Association and the Scarab Club.
  - Passports, 1905-1925 (Box 1)
  - Identification, Registration, and Membership Cards, 1928-1931 (Box 1)
- Letters, 1899-1931, Series 2:; (Box 1; 19 folders)
  Scattered letters are primarily between members of the Waltensperger family describing their travels. One letter from Waltensperger briefly mentions classes at the Académie des Beaux Arts and his instructor, Jean-Léon Gérôme, “who is perhaps the best that ever happened. He is very severe and no fancy stuff goes with him.”
  Letters are arranged chronologically.
  - Letters, undated (Box 1)
  - Letters, 1899 (Box 1)
  - Letters, 1905 (Box 1)
  - Letters, 1906 (Box 1)
  - Letters, 1914-1918 (Box 1)
  - Letters, 1920-1924 (Box 1)
  - Letters, 1925 (Box 1)
  - Letters, 1926 (Box 1)
  - Letters, 1927-1928 (Box 1)
  - Letters, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Letters, 1930, (4 folders) (Box 1)
  - Letters, 1931, (5 folders) (Box 1)
- Business Records, 1925-1931, Series 3:; (Box 1; 4 folders)
  Business records include handwritten account books listing prices and sales of artwork, a bank book listing financial transactions, and studio inventories listing prices for artwork and studio furnishings. Also included are miscellaneous receipts for frames, shipment of artwork, travel expenses, and insurance payments.
  - Account Books and Bank Book, 1925-1929 (Box 1)
  - Studio Inventory Lists, 1926, undated (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Receipts, 1925-1931, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1)
- Engagement Diaries, 1914-1931, Series 4:; (Box 1; 6 folders)
  Twelve engagement diaries contain very brief entries describing daily activities, small drawings, and miscellaneous annotations.
  Diaries are arranged chronologically.
  - Engagement Diaries, 1914-1918 (Box 1)
  - Engagement Diaries, 1919-1920 (Box 1)
  - Engagement Diaries, 1921-1922 (Box 1)
  - Engagement Diaries, 1923-1925 (Box 1)
  - Engagement Diaries, 1927 (Box 1)
  - Engagement Diaries, 1928-1931 (Box 1)
- Notes and Writings, 1913-1931, Series 5:; (Box 1; 8 folders)
  This series primarily consists of notebooks that contain miscellaneous addresses, notes on light and color, and annotated sketches. There are also addresses of models and miscellaneous notes primarily concerning Waltensperger's thoughts about painting and other art-related topics.
  - Notebooks, 1913-1931, undated, (5 folders) (Box 1)
  - Addresses of Models, 1931, undated (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, 1924, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1)
- Artwork, circa 1890-circa 1930, Series 6:; (Box 1; 1 folder)
  Artwork consists of loose sketches by Waltensperger of human figures and a peacock.
  - Loose sketches, circa 1890-circa 1930 (Box 1)
- Printed Material, 1896-1931, Series 7:; (Box 1; 19 folders)
  Printed material includes clippings concerning art, health, and financial investment, exhibition announcements and catalogs for Waltensperger and others, a Scarab Club yearbook, travel brochures, brochures concerning Christian topics, and miscellaneous printed material.
  - Clippings, undated, (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - Clippings, 1896-1898 (Box 1)
  - Clippings, 1912-1915 (Box 1)
  - Clippings, 1916-1918 (Box 1)
  - Clippings, 1926-1927 (Box 1)
  - Clippings, 1928 (Box 1)
  - Clippings, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Clippings, 1930 (Box 1)
  - Clippings, 1931 (Box 1)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs for Waltensperger, 1927-1929 (Box 1)
  - Exhibition Catalog for Others, 1915 (Box 1)
  - Scarab Club Yearbook, 1928 (Box 1)
  - Travel Brochures, 1925-1928, undated (Box 1)
  - Brochures Concerning Christian Topics, 1914-1930, undated (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Brochures, 1931, undated (Box 1)
  - Books, The Bible and The Merchant of Venice, 1917, undated (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, undated (Box 1)
- Photographs, circa 1890-circa 1930, Series 8:; (Boxes 1-2; 25 folders)
  Photographs are of Waltensperger, an art class at the Académie Julian, and of Waltensperger's family and friends. Travel photographs show scenes in New England and Europe, including Belgium, Holland, and Italy. There are also photographs relating to various topics of interest to Waltensperger.
  - Photographs of Waltensperger, undated (Box 1)
  - Photograph of Waltensperger and Art Students at the Académie Julian, 1893 (Box 1)
  - Photographs of Friends, undated, (6 folders) (Box 1)
  - Photographs of Native Americans, undated (Box 2 (pam))
  - Photographs of Miscellaneous Children, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2 (pam))
  - Photographs of Miscellaneous Animals, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2 (pam))
  - Photographs of New England Scenes, undated, (6 folders) (Box 2 (pam))
  - Photographs of European Scenes, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2 (pam))
  - Photographs of Miscellaneous Houses, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2 (pam))
  - Photographs of Artwork, undated (Box 2 (pam))
  - Unprinted Negatives, undated (Box 2 (pam))